[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the ITE
computer society and by it e software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[Music]
Welcome to software engineering radio.
I'm your host Jovanas Prony and today
I'll be discussing observability in the
tool chain with Brian Dear. Brian is a
developer advocate at Gradle, a Java
Champion and Apache member who
contributes to the directory Maven and
Shirro projects. He spends much of his
day contributing to OSS projects by
writing code, tutorials, blogs, and
answering questions. Brian, welcome to
Software Engineering Radio. Is there
anything I miss that you'd like to add?
Yeah, well, thanks for having me. I
think that bio pretty much covers it. I
think the only other thing I'll add is
most of my career has kind of been in
and around the Java world. So everything
I think about is sort of skewed a little
in that direction, but I think
everything we're going to talk about
today applies to just about any
developer. Okay. So let's start now.
Tool chains. In software development, we
have several tool chains. Compiler tool
chain, build tool chain, CI/CD tool
chain, lots of tool chains. What tool
chains are we referring to here? I think
the answer is yes, all of them. So I
think the issue really is exactly what
you mentioned, right? We have all of
these tools. They're complex. They're
all kind of tied together. Some of them
are stitched together better than
others. So, we really need a better way
to understand them. Okay. We'll be
talking about all the tool chains we'll
be using here. Yeah. Yes. Good. Now,
when we talk about observability in the
tool chain, what are the similarities
and differences with the observability
of systems running production? Because
usually when we talk about
observability, we think about the system
in production and the various events,
logs and things we can get to understand
what is happening there. So are there
any similarities with this? Yeah,
absolutely. Absolutely. So if we think
about our production applications,
right, you wouldn't deploy a production
application today without any kind of
monitoring or anything behind it, right?
And a lot of that is because they're
complex. We don't really know the load
on the system or all these other things
we are unaware of until that I don't
know Black Friday event happens or
whatever. Our build tools are very
complex systems or build chains
everything are very complex right you
have all these things happening
downloading dependencies compiling
linting unit tests integration tests
whatever there's security scanning lots
of things that can go wrong just like
our production applications. So to me,
it's kind of mindboggling to think about
that we're just now getting to a point
where we're treating the complexity of
our build tools the same way as we would
our applications, right? So if something
goes wrong in your build tool, how do
you deploy something to production?
Well, you can't, right? So if your build
tools are actually in line, they're on
the path to getting something deployed
to production. And also, is there any
relationship with the shifting of
servability left? This is something that
you find a lot nowadays that is pretty
much feeding observability data from the
system production to basically the
developers for the day-to-day
activities. Is there any relationship
between observability in the tool chain
and this shift left of the observability
of the system? Absolutely. I think one
of my favorite things to talk about is
flaky test for example. Right. So flaky
test, I may mention this a few times,
but if you haven't ever been aware of
flaky test, it's a test that essentially
will pass one minute and then without
any code changes will fail the next
minute or vice versa, or works in my
machine, but not your machine. It works
on CI but not locally, whatever it is,
there's some inherent flakiness. So the
earlier developers can know about those
types of problems, the better they can
spend their time. So if I'm working on a
feature and there's a flaky test, for
example, that has nothing to do with my
code that I'm changing, just the fact
that I'm aware of that will make it so I
don't go hunt down that issue. Right
now, there's a lot of other problems
with flaky tests. We can talk about how
fixing them and how to monitor them and
all that, but essentially that's just
one example of a developer having
knowledge earlier in in the system is
better. Okay. And in terms of problems
that is observability in the tool chain
now what problems are we are actually
trying to address with this? So you
mentioned flaky test and maybe also
security scanning some other stuff but
in general what are we trying to achieve
here? I think one of the biggest ones
that I know at Gradle we talk about a
lot is developer feedback cycles, right?
So oftent times we run into issues where
builds are hours long, right? I know of
a lot of shops who don't run their tests
locally. They let their CI systems
handle everything. So they can't even
run their test. So their feedback cycles
are incredibly long and very
disconnected. So again, that kind of
goes to shifting left. If I can't even
run my tests, then there's no way I'm
going to be able to be productive,
right? So, I'm going to make some code
changes. I don't know, throw some salt
over my shoulder and then push the CI,
right? Or push my git repository and
then CI is going to pick it up and then
maybe an hour or two later, I'll get the
feedback for my test. So, there's no way
that I can be productive in that
environment. But even in the case of if
I can run tests locally, if my feedback
cycle is let's say 20 minutes, I run a
build, you know, I make some changes and
I run some build. So whatever that
includes, linting, compiling, testing,
whatever your build includes, all of
those things, if my feedback loop is 20
minutes, well, how many times can I do
that a day, right? And some people
listening to this may be thinking 20
minutes is fast, right? But even if you
can get that down to 2 minutes, just
think about if you and I were silent for
2 minutes, right? People would be
checking their phones or whatever to see
if this thing is actually working. or if
you were having a conversation with
somebody and you waited for 2 minutes
before you said the next word, you'd
probably just turn around and walk off.
So, we really need to think about
feedback cycles being as fast as
possible. But again, using from the
perspective of observability, we need to
have data to figure out how long those
feedback cycles are and then of course
data to know where the bottlenecks are
to improve them. Okay. So, it's really
is about here efficiency and
productivity. Am I correct? These are
the kind of things I think that's one
angle. I think the biggest angle we see
is definitely productivity but I think
there's a lot of other angles too. So
just by having data something goes wrong
you can figure it out. So maybe you can
think of efficiency as in
troubleshooting efficiency but also if
you don't know what dependencies you're
using right so you're just not aware of
what is in the system to begin with.
That is actually quite an interesting
one. I think in the Java world probably
is a problem that is very often
presented quite it's a big problem.
I remember with having classps with
different versions of the same jar in
the same class path because people
forgot to remove some dependencies and
then strange behaviors happening.
Absolutely. I mean we still see those
today. So that's a problem that and it
was probably more popular earlier in my
career but we still see echoes of that
now where things change packages or
namespaces. So you can still end up with
basically two of the same thing on your
class path which just adds to the
complexity and without either a great
deal of knowledge about how the system
works it's really difficult to find
unless you have some tooling around the
system. Okay. And so I guess this aspect
of observability is around also well is
about developer productivity engineering
as well isn't it? Absolutely.
Absolutely. So developer productivity
engineering or DPE is basically all
about engineering our way into making
our builds faster or basically the
feedback cycles shorter so I can get
more done. I can stay in the flow,
right? As a developer, what I really
want to do is write code. So if I'm
spending a long period of time not
writing code or not waiting for a long
process to happen, that's less time I'm
going to be active or excited about
whatever I'm working on. Okay. So it's
not only about productivity, but it's
also about developer experience then. So
it's both things. I think those two
things are very related depending on who
you talk to, depending on how much they
like software, but I think if you've
been in the industry for more than a few
years, you know, if you like writing
code, right? And if you don't, you're
probably migrating away from banging on
the keyboard every day. But if you do
enjoy that, then you want to be
productive. You want to learn, you want
to get the little hits of dopamine every
time you get some feedback, right? So
maybe you run a test in your IDE and it
goes green, right? That little bit of
feedback is exciting to your brain and
it makes you happy. And I keep saying
that a happy developer is a productive
developer. So it's a win-win all around.
Win for me because I'm a happy person.
It's a win for the company that I work
for because I'm more productive.
Essentially, me being productive saves
them money or makes them money depending
on how you look at it. True. Yeah. Yeah.
I can see the the usefulness of this
solving some of those irritations that
you have every day when tools don't work
well or you have to wait for stuff.
Absolutely. Yeah, I can understand that.
I can see it being a developer myself.
And in terms of observability here, what
are we observing? So, can you give us
some example of what kind of information
data we are looking for here? Sure. I
think it depends on what your problems
are, but essentially you can kind of
think about them as in I guess the
original three pillars of observability.
So I think starting with logs, logs is
the easy one, right? Build tools have
all kinds of logs. In some cases, too
many logs. So you know if you have a
million line of code project, regardless
of what your build is doing, that's
going to output a lot of logs. So how do
you sift through that, right? And it's
the same with our applications in
production. If you have a lot of logs,
you need tools to just cut through them
and sort them and and whatever. But
yeah, so tracing. So where are your
bottlenecks in your build? So in a lot
of cases, it's testing, right? We've
seen a lot of shops where 80 90% of your
build time is testing. So whenever I
talk about builds, I include test time,
right? I know not everybody does that
because a lot of people like to skip
their tests, but I won't go down that
path, right? So finding bottlenecks in
your builds and then metrics like build
times, how long are your build times? If
build time is the issue, right? If
you're measuring feedback cycles, if you
don't measure what those feedback cycles
are, how are you going to improve them,
right? Or how do you know when they get
worse or better? So how do you report
success to your boss who's paying you to
improve your feedback times or whatever?
Yeah. Okay. And in terms of what we can
do currently, what kind of observability
options the tools currently offer? I
think right now there's not a lot out
there. I mean, I know our product. So,
so I work at Gradle. We have a product
called De Velocity who works in the Java
world that obviously specializes in this
very thing we're talking about. But in
general, I don't think that tooling is
very robust in a lot of systems. And
that's all the way down to the
individual tools themselves like
compilers, llinters. They may not even
output a lot of data that you want to
consume. So I think we're starting to
see more robust data come out of these
tools and I think it goes handinhand
with a lot of the supply chain security
that's happening too because we want to
know what goes into the system we want
to know what comes out of the system for
security reasons but we can also use
that same mechanism to gather
information to improve the lives for
everybody and so at the moment so you
said the tools don't really offer much
so in practice is there something that
we can still do with what we've got at
the moment in terms of observability in
the tool chain absolely Absolutely.
Yeah. So, I think even without
specialized tools, just measuring how
long a process takes or individual
executions in your pipeline take, right?
You could do that, dump it to a file or
dump it to a database somewhere and
that's a pretty lowhanging fruit, right?
It's not a lot of data. It's not rich
data, but if you don't have anything,
that's a huge improvement. And then at
least you have enough data to make
decisions on where to invest or where to
spend effort in collecting more
information. with all these tools you
mentioned compilers you mentioned tools
to basically security scanning maybe
test runs things that break or instead
of running and all this so several tools
different data potentially an enormous
amount of data I'm think also especially
like logs I remember well in the Java
world actually when you compile stuff is
common to see logs warnings so all sorts
of stuff lots of information there how
are we supposed to collect this data
make sense of it. So with the current
tools, you said we don't have much but
how can we make sense of it? That's a
great point. So let's take the example
of uh compilation either I don't know
maybe you want to talk about warnings or
deprecations or whatever it is right so
if you are running a build right and I'm
just going to wait 2 minutes or 10
minutes or an hour for my build to
happen I'm not going to sit and watch
those logs go by right and I'm not going
to go proactively look for when that
happens right after an hour I'm not
going to go back and scroll through
every line looking for compiler warnings
I got a green light it passed right So
the real way to fix that is either make
the warnings errors, right? So that's
kind of like the hard heavy-handed
approach or have some system in place
where you're tracking the amount of
warnings you have now and then you're
reducing them, right? So you have to
have some system sitting on top that
looks for this. So say you have 100
compiler warnings today and by the end
of the next 3 months you want to get it
down to 10 or zero or whatever. So you
have to track that number, right? And
you have to watch it go down. So you
have to have some tooling that collects
that information and report on it and be
actionable on it because if nobody looks
for that data, nobody's going to act on
it. Yeah. And so have you seen anything
at the moment any teams any real
projects where people are doing this at
the right now? Have you experienced
anything like that? I think especially
in the case of flaky tests. So going
back to testing, I think that's a huge
problem. So it's a similar issue, right?
It's a giant time suck for some teams.
I've worked at shops where the flaky
test notification was an email that went
out to all of engineering. Well, that's
fine if there's like 10 of you. It's
probably less fine if there's hundreds
of you, right? Or thousands of you. That
system does not scale. So, the ability
to collect that information and act on
it is critical. So, you need to in the
flaky test, whatever your company wants
to do, whether it's move those tests
into quarantine, disable the tests,
assign somebody to fix the test,
whatever it is, right? rerun the test
potentially, right? If it's flaky, maybe
just rerun it a bunch of times and and
we'll pass. That's an okay stop gap, but
you need to have a way to both work
around these issues and to continue on
to improve. Okay. Now, also, as you
probably know, there is a lot of talking
about the use of AI in software
development. It seems that I mean, this
is the most discussed subject among
developers at the moment with all sorts
of opinions around it. uh something that
I think we can say is that the use of AI
during the day-to-day work actually
introduces some interesting challenges
in terms of observability in the tool
chain because now there is generated AI
code. So perhaps we need to know the
provenence maybe for security reasons or
other reasons and maybe copyrights who
knows but anyway in general what do you
think are the issues introduced by this
new tooling in this respect? Yeah, I
knew we were going to talk about AI,
right? Every conversation now has AI in
it. And like you said, love it or hate
it, I think it's here. It's not going
away. We have to get used to it. So, we
have to be aware of these types of
challenges. The Providence one is a
great one. So, where did this code come
from, right? So, there's a whole bunch
of tooling around sort of providence and
access stations that we could get into,
but that's one way to record where
information came from. But just the
sheer fact that more code is going to
enter their system means you have to
have smarter tools around it. Right? So
let's say you're using I don't know
copilot, right? So that's just helping
you write code. So you're the one
writing code. Copilot's helping you. We
have no information where that code came
from, right? But is copilot helping your
organization? I don't know. Right? You
can ask developers. They're like, "Yeah,
I like it." Right? But is it actually
helping you deliver features faster? You
have to measure something, right? Maybe
measure the number of features you push
to production or how often you have pull
requests, whatever it is. That's some
measure. So you need some tooling around
that to measure the productivity of that
tool for example. But what else I
mentioned that more code is coming into
the system, right? So that means we have
more code to compile. Going back to
warnings, maybe there's more warnings.
Testing becomes more important, right?
and then maybe even policies like so if
I'm generating code and generating my
tests what have I done right I haven't
actually done anything like I'm just
running some generated code and
generated tests those generated tests
aren't doing anything for me because
they were generated from the same source
that ran the tests on one hand it is
good because it's going to detect if it
changes the behavior in the future but I
don't know anyway I'm going to get into
some philosophical issues here in a
minute so I think AI adds a tremendous
amount of complexity
into our systems just from the sheer
volume it's going to add. So how can
observability help us dealing with this
complexity or at least understand what
is going on and decide if it is a good
thing or a bad thing depending on the
situation. Yeah. So again I think it
comes back to being able to track data
right so if your code base is growing
end over end your build times are going
to get longer. That's just how it works,
right? You have more code takes longer
to do whatever it is you're going to
test. So, you have to have some sort of
data around that to really look at and
figure out is this how we want to
structure our code. Now, if our code
base is growing, I don't know, a million
lines a year, whatever, 10,000 lines a
year, whatever that number is, is that
sustainable? Do I need to break up my
project into multiple projects? Spread
them across repositories, spread them
across teams, whatever it is. and you
still need data to make smart decisions
based on that, right? And maybe it's not
an issue, right? So that's another good
thing that data can provide you. So
maybe you are adding time, but you're
using other techniques like there's a
bunch of build acceleration techniques
where like build caching, compiler
avoidance, predictive test selection,
all these other types of techniques that
are out there that can speed up your
build. So maybe that increased amount of
code that you're adding doesn't actually
cause kind of a regress in the developer
experience. Do you think also that AI
can actually help as well with this with
observability or in the tool chain?
Yeah, I think there's a number of ways.
I think just the pattern matching alone
from AI does this failure look like this
failure or say does one failure look
like another failure and categorize
them. So in testing for example, if you
could lump test failures together, then
a developer could probably make really
informed decisions on which types of
tests are more important to fix first.
Now if those are flaky tests, that's one
thing. If there are test failures cuz I
made a code change, that might be a
different problem. But maybe it's an
infrastructural problem. So, a lot of
builds are really complex. They're
downloading things from various systems,
but the internet's flaky, right? It's
just how it is. There's always going to
be connection errors, servers are down,
whatever. So, there's probably a lot of
analytics that can happen just analyzing
are these types of problems
infrastructure problems? If so, that's
not a developer's problem. Maybe we can
automatically rerun a build for them.
Maybe we can signal, hey, we think this
is not your fault. Don't worry about
spending the next hour of your life
trying to figure out why it's your
problem. You are referring to things
like downloading some dependencies with
Maven or Gradle or something else that
could be subject to flakiness if you
have not cached them locally for example
things like this. Yes, absolutely. And
how we do CI sort of changed over the
last I since the last few years but over
the last 10 20 years anyway. So we used
to have these longunning agents. Now
everyone favors ephemeral builds, right?
So now we're downloading more of the
world on every build. And of course
there are caching techniques around
that, right? But again, observability
data, knowing how long your build takes,
knowing what portion of your build was
downloading dependencies might actually
be useful. So if you have a large
dependency download time of your every
build, maybe that's a signal that that
build isn't configured to use a
dependency cache or whatever. So, I know
GitHub and Jenkins have a cache system
they can use to save your dependencies.
There are other tools, like I said,
build caches and and things that work a
little different, but that's one
indication of having data helps you
pinpoint those projects that potentially
have problems. Okay. And have you seen
any teams doing that? Implementing some
observability for the AI they're using,
for example. Have you seen any? Yes. So,
we have a lot of customers that are
doing exactly that. Dependency download
time is a huge problem for a lot of our
customers for exactly what I just
mentioned. They were on Jenkins two
years ago where they had these really
long running agents and they switched to
ephemeral builds and look now their
builds are so much longer. What
happened? Why isn't the new system
working better than the old system?
Well, it ends up being because your
build actually changed. Now you're
downloading a bunch of things. or we had
one case where the network file storage
that the build agent was using was
slower than the previous system, right?
So, how do you track that? Right? The
dis IO is essentially slower. So,
without monitoring the dis IO, there's
no way a developer is going to know what
happened. First things, what's going to
happen is, well, I like the old system.
The new one sucks, right? Well, that's
not the true story, right? The new one
isn't configured the same way, so maybe
we should fix that. Yeah. Okay.
something again related maybe to AI
again we mentioned this the code
provenence but now with all these
developers using AI well according to
some surveys is like 90% of developers
in the world are using AI but I'm not
sure how much we can trust those numbers
because usually they come from companies
with an interest in the outcome but
there are still lots of developers using
AI assistant so how critical is called
provenance tracking in these tool chains
for you because of this usage I think
it's very critical. I think we're
starting to see more interest in the
open source community. I think that's
kind of where it's going to start
because as companies consume open
source, right? I don't know what
percentage it is. I think Tidelift put
out a report a few years ago, but it's
some insanely large percentage of your
applications are open source, right? So,
I think open source is also the area
that moves faster, adopts new
functionality faster. So what we're
seeing is I think open source
foundations are going to be more
interested in providence of source. So I
know for example when you bring a new
project to Apache right there's a big
audit as far as do we have the
capability of taking on the ownership of
this source. So that's I have some
source I'm bringing it one place but as
we're incrementally adding source
nobody's really doing anything. There
are a lot of snippet detection in a lot
of these tools out there but I think
they're questionable at best. So yeah.
So anyway, so I think we probably should
be doing more for tracking providence of
code from individual developers, from
AI, from systems, wherever it is.
Personally, I don't know of tools that
are doing that now. But I do know we're
starting to get into the world where
we're tracking the providence of where
things were created, right? Where things
were built. I don't think we're going to
get to the individual lines of code
until we've solved the output problem.
Well, hey guys, at some point we'll need
to get there because have you seen what
is happening also with some open source
software that some malicious actors hack
them like the SSH issue with adding
vulnerabilities. So probably some XC
utils I think those types of problems
are going to be bigger to deal with. So
there's some social engineering aspect
to that but just the increase amount of
code that's coming in from AI right good
or bad means that the volume of change
is happening quicker. So maybe you're,
you know, your open source project or
your corporate project is getting, I
don't know, 10 changes a week, right?
Just some random number. 10 changes a
week. That's a very reasonable number
where somebody, one person could sit
down and and review those code changes,
whatever. You know, you can you can
scale that by whatever you want. But as
soon as you, you know, 10x that number,
that problem gets much harder. And doing
thorough reviews of your code is harder.
So we're going to need better tooling
around, you know, quality gates. All of
these things need to be automated. The
human eyeball is probably less a factor
here and more a factor of is this code
readable not so much is it correct. And
now let's look into maybe how to improve
the observability in our tool chain. So
the first question I have is obviously
related to the business. Yeah, we say we
want to have better observability in our
tool chain and somebody from the
business side can say why this is going
to cost me money. what am I going to get
out of it? Yeah. So my response would be
why do we have observability in our
production applications right I mean the
answer that from the business side is
probably some sort of risk answer right
something goes down capacity planning
right we do capacity planning so things
don't go down right it all kind of comes
back to risk right something goes down
how long does it take to bring back up
so my troubleshooting window is smaller
so the same thing happens for our build
tools right so if something happens we
want that the resolution to that issue
to be shorter or again we want our
developer feedback cycles to be shorter
so we can be more productive and and
essentially being more productive faster
time to market I can increase the number
of features that I'm working on or my
team is working on that's the business
reason I think have you got any examples
from real projects about this as well
because I gradually just mentioned about
customers with the length of the builds
and this kind of stuff build time has
been our bread and butter I think that's
where our build acceleration technology
technologies has really been big for us.
But the only reason why they work is
because of the observability data,
right? So you want to find a bottleneck
in your build. Well, you need to monitor
and and have, you know, detailed
information about your build. But let's
just say we've had customers massively
overprovision build agents for example,
right? So I mentioned issues with disio,
right? But let's just say you're paying
for a cloud compute and your builds are
only using I don't know 10 25% of your
CPU, right? So you could probably save a
ton of money by using smaller build
agents assuming they're in the cloud,
right? If they're in somebody's closet
somewhere, you know, in your basement,
then that compute is already paid for.
But in the cloud, you're paying, you
know, per minute or or whatever. So
there's some serious gains to happen
there. But usually what happens is
nobody monitors that. So my bill is what
it is. I'm going to throw more hardware
at it to make it go faster. But, you
know, there's a I don't know, it's not
IObound or or or it's not a CPU bound or
maybe it is, but it's limited to one
thread, right? So, you know, I have four
CPUs on my system and I can only really
make use of one of them. So, I'm just
throwing dollars out the window. So,
we've seen a handful of cases like that.
And the opposite is true. So, we've seen
cases where customers are overutilized.
So, their agents are not provisioned big
enough. a few years ago when the Mac
switched to Apple silicone. So at Gradel
in-house, we did some some performance
benchmarks for for ourself using our own
product of course, but we found out that
our builds, you know, for Gradle build
tool and and de velocity were faster on
the Apple silicone max than the Intel
Max, right? And it was such a difference
where it actually made sense to buy
developers new laptops, right? Which
makes everybody happy, right? The
company's actually saving money. The
developers get a new flashy laptop. So,
it's a win-win all around. But again,
you can only do these things with data.
With data. Yeah. In your experience,
what are the considerations a team
should actually make to decide between
adding more observability to the tool
chain or simplifying the system they've
created because I guess the more complex
the system, the more observability you
need or the more complicated the tool
chain may be. But so, have you come
across situations where say, well, you
know what? Have you considered making a
simpler system that will give you a
better bang for the buck? I haven't, but
that's a great point. I know I talk
about this a lot when I talk about
choosing build tools. So, for folks not
in the Java world, I'm a Maven fan,
which is there's two big Java build
tools. There's Maven and Gradel. I'm a
big fan of the Maven tool, and then of
course, I work at the other company,
which is a very interesting mix, right?
So there's a lot of discussion around
about simplicity and speed and and which
one's better, which one makes you more
productive, which is great and
interesting, but I do think that's an
important thing to consider. I think our
build systems are really complex because
I can write code to do whatever I want,
right? It doesn't mean I always should
do that, right? So I think simplifying
your system is is in your best benefit,
but again, how do you know your change
made an impact, right? If you don't have
any data to start with and you make some
change, you're like it's better now.
Well, better than what right? So, you
should start with some observability
anyway. This is what you're saying
something, right? So, if you're going to
make a change, you know, even if it's
just doing some basic, you know, back of
the envelope benchmarks and then making
a change and then doing them again, I
still think that's a great win. I also
was thinking about things. Have you seen
that now there is many teams are moving
back from micros service based
architecture to monolith ones or
sometimes maybe still service based but
instead of having a gazillion of them
having three things I kind of reducing
the number and that of course reduces
the pipelines the build systems and and
everything else. So I was think also in
those terms as well. So there is a red
reduction of complexity not necessarily
compile time depending on how the
systems are written but right. So, I
know of a couple customers that have
more than 10,000 different repositories,
right? So, how do you manage that
without any kind of tooling? How do you
manage that? Take the simple case of
upgrading a component, whatever build
system you're into, you're all going to
have the same problems. You either want
to update a dependency, a runtime
library, you know, whatever. So, if I
want to update from some old version of
Java to a new version of Java, and I
have 10,000 repos, I don't know, let's
say 60% of them are Java, you know, 40%
are Node or whatever. So, first I need
to know which of those repos that affect
me, which ones are using the older
version, which ones are not using the
newer version, which ones are using, you
know, a version somewhere in the middle,
right? That maybe don't need attention
now, but they will next time I want to
make this change. But you can't manage
that that amount of code in that many
different places without some sort of
tooling. Again, you know, maybe in in
some cases it's some basic code scanning
in some inventory app that you run
inhouse, right? And that's fine, but
obviously I think tracking as you build
these things, each project gives you
better detailed information. You know,
you'll know how long it takes to to
build, where the dependencies come from,
which versions of all of the all of your
your tools you're using. It'll give you
a lot richer information where you can
improve this system. Yeah. Now, let's
say that company they decide somebody
decides, yeah, we need more
observability here. What are the
organizational and cultural changes
necessary to implement that? I tell you
what I'm thinking about. You see when I
work with uh companies very often I find
that when there are complex systems
maybe with many teams there are
situations where nobody looks at the
build and the broken tests something
breaks it's not my problem it's somebody
else's problem. So in those situations
you can have all the observability you
want but if nobody looks at the system
at the data and the information nothing
will happen. So in your experience, what
kind of changes have to happen in the
organization for this implementation of
more observability to succeed? I
definitely think there's a little bit of
education that needs to be involved. You
know, some developers are going to get
it, right? If I'm troubleshooting issue
and the more information I have, I know
that should right in theory make it
easier for me to troubleshoot an issue.
We've seen cases where the issue the
kind of enforcement of observability
comes from your CI team. So there's a
lot of bigger shops that as long as if
there's a CI issue, what happens is a
developer is like, oh, it's not my
problem. I'm going to open a ticket and
this central CI build tool team will
look at it, right? And they don't know
what to do unless it's uh some sort of
centralized common tooling problem.
There's nothing they can do about it. So
what they implemented is we have a
product called build scans but it's
essentially a detailed view of all of
the information that happened in your
build. So what they've done is they've
said you can't open a ticket with the
central team without this observability
data. But the fact that you have that
observability data means that someone
can probably look at it before sending
it to the CI team. So that was one way
that that other team kind of enforced
that the data exists you know for them
essentially but also because it exists
it makes it easier for the developer to
kind of self- select should I fix this
or is this somebody else's problem okay
and in terms of data so we have many
tools as we had observability how can we
avoid being submerged by deluge of data
so how do we select what to observe yeah
that's a great one part of me wants to
say just observe everything right and
then you can use that data as needed but
you know there's there's obviously cost
considerations timing considerations so
I would say start with the problems that
are bothering you the most right so
again we we start talking about
developer experience if feedback cycles
are the thing you want to improve then
obviously the timing of things is at the
forefront right so measure CI times
measure local developer time so builds
on local developer machines you can
measure how long it takes for something
to fail So obviously if your build's an
hour and most of your failures happen in
the first 30 seconds, that's really
good. That's probably an ideal case,
right? But that's kind of where you'd
want to be. So measuring the the basics
first and then you can do the simple
things like how often are your
developers running builds, right? So if
your build is an hour, you can only do
that a couple times a day. So if you can
shave, I don't know, 20 minutes off it,
maybe you can do three, four times a
day. So that'll improve productivity.
It'll improve throughput. It'll improve
your CI your CIQ time should go down
because your builds are smaller. There's
a lot of information just in that basic
measurement of time that will help
improve. And of course, you know, if you
want to get into kind of the security
angle, like really monitoring your
dependencies and those things, that's
obviously a bit more involved. But I
think starting with some of the basics
to just get an understanding of where
you're at is a win. But it's up to the
company like find your problem in focus
on measuring that and then what's going
to happen is you're going to have the
aha moment or the that wasn't actually
the problem it's this. But because
you're starting from somewhere it's a
lot easier to incrementally improve your
position than than you know go from 0 to
60. Okay let's say now okay the company
sold they want to do this but and they
have a green field project to start
with. How can they start? So say in a
green field project, how would you
approach this adding observability to
the tool chain? That's a good one. I
think that might actually be harder
because you don't have anything to
compare it against, right? But it's also
good because there's no preconceived
notions of the types of data that you
need, right? The problems that you're
currently having. So again, I would
start small, right? So instrument
everything. So whatever tooling you're
using that supports any kind of
instrumentation or or data collection, I
would do that. If you're a shop that
uses some sort of logging service, you
can even dump your builds into a logging
system. That's still better than
nothing. That probably gets expensive
really quick. But I would say start
start collecting data. I think you need
to also make some sort of decisions on
that data. So not just collect it, but
also, you know, maybe some sort of
alerting, right? So again, I keep
beating the build time metric, but it's
an easy one. Or or flaky test. Let's go
back to flaky test. So percentage of
flaky tests if that raises more than say
2%. You need to alert somebody. So there
needs to be some actionable event that
happens. And if you're starting with a
green field application, maybe that's a
really really low threshold, right? And
maybe it's always going to stay that way
or there's always some inherent
flakiness with systems now. But starting
with a low number, being able to do some
alerting, whatever it is, you know,
create a Slackbot, create an email, open
an issue automatically, whatever it is,
assign the issue to somebody to fix
right away. That way, the data that
you're collecting is actionable and it's
being used. And what about also you know
even if there isn't a lot of data in
addition to what you say actually an
approach could be also a reason to do
something from the beginning would be to
set up the necessary infrastructure to
actually being able to collect the data
in the first place. That is what you
said pretty much instrument every tool
that has some gives you the possibility
to add some instrumentation and
collecting data just do that. So I would
imagine that even if you don't use the
data at the beginning, just having the
infrastructure to collect it and put it
somewhere could be useful. I agree the
amount of learning that your team will
gain. So whether it's your the
development team working on the green
field application, some centralized team
that's supporting them with the
observability infrastructure, it's a
very lowrisk way to gain organizational
knowledge around that and then start
figuring out the questions you want to
answer and then you could scale from
that green field project to other
projects. And then the other question is
of course for for legacy systems which
from your previous answers I would
imagine that this is the easier part
because you have data now or you know
what to look for I think so I think you
at least have some questions that you
want answered right so usually is this
thing slow or it I don't know that's a
big one right so if you have again a
million lines of code and is this thing
slow the obvious answer is yes right why
is it slow because it's a million lines
of code right but that's not really like
an actionable answer you can't well I'll
just delete half the code you can't do
that right but there are things you
could do you know what percentage of the
time is running tests it's probably a
large portion but maybe linting is
actually 5 minutes of that so I love
linting I love all of these quality
static analysis tools but a lot of them
can be hooked up in your IDE right and
so the incremental cost of running them
is almost nothing right I type a line
and instantly my IDE gives me a red
squiggly line or or some warning or
whatever so if that's the case if I'm
already getting that feedback, then I
probably don't need it when I run local
builds, right? I probably do need it in
CI to make sure those things don't
actually happen and people aren't
ignoring, you know, IDE warnings, but
that could be 5 minutes off your build
that you cut off. Now, 5 minutes over an
hour, maybe that doesn't move the needle
for you, but that is something, right?
And and there's probably a lot of those
types of events that happen that can be
improved, you know, over time. But I
guess that on the other hand in legacy
systems depending what you're doing
might be difficult to instrument the
code and act on it as well because I'm
thinking about for example security
issues. It's like if you start looking
for them and you never done that before,
you may end up in a situation where you
have a pile of them and you cannot
really stop building your system until
all of them are sold. So you need to
have a prioritization of sorts.
Absolutely. and and there's a handful of
tools that will help with that for like
security scanning specifically, right?
But I think that's another one of those
types of issues where you incrementally
improve, right? So if you have a
thousand security issues today, you want
to make sure that number doesn't
increase, right? And then and then
hopefully, you know, you target that
number and you can slowly drop it or
quickly drop it would be better. But a
lot of build systems are older systems,
legacy systems are overly complex. You
know, they've migrated between versions
of tools. They're in states of
migration, right? I know one system that
I worked on a few years ago that was
migrated from Ant. So in the Java world,
Ant is this pretty legacy build tool.
What happens with a lot of these
migrations is it was migrated enough to
work with a new system and then there's
still a lot of tech debt, right? Or or
build rot or tech debt that's in the
system that was just never cleaned up.
But it actually affects, you know, the
performance of the system, how easy it
is to add new tools. Again, if you
wanted to add a new security scanner,
even that becomes harder because, you
know, there's always these special
little edge cases around the tool. So,
you know, going back to the
simplification of our our systems, you
know, there's a lot to be said for that,
but just knowing where the complexity is
again is still valuable information. And
for teams that are new to tool chain
observability, have you got any
suggestions about metrics? First step
matrix, you know, okay, we want to have
some observability. what we start to
look for. I think build time is the easy
one. I think that's the one that is the
easiest to comprehend for folks. And I
know I keep saying it, but it's like
test coverage, right? So, there's a lot
of people who hate the test coverage
metric because it can be abused or
gamed, but I find it still a very
valuable
metric. Just, you know, you take it with
a grain of salt. So again, take build
time with a grain of salt for example,
but it's a really easy one to measure
and to improve and to know if there's a
problem. So you know, there's a lot of
science that that talks about context
switching. So how long it takes your
brain to to context switch. Basically,
if your feedback cycle is over some
number of minutes, it's actually it does
you a disservice, right? So I think the
science says it takes 10 minutes to
context switch away from something to be
productive again and then 10 minutes to
switch back, right? So that's basically
10 minutes of time. So if my build is
say 20 minutes, right? That's probably
the worst case scenario. So I start the
build and what's going to happen is I
know it's going to take 20 minutes. So
I'm going to go check my email, right?
And then it's going to take me 10
minutes to kind of focus on my email. So
that's an extra 10 minutes I wasted. And
then eventually I'm going to come back
to my build. And it failed. It failed,
you know, whatever 6 minutes into the
build. And I've been sitting on my
hands, you know, you know, scrolling
through my email for the last half hour.
So I go back, I was like, "Oh, you know,
it's some something silly like I missed
the semicolon or or some silly change."
I fix it and I start the whole process
over again, right? So, you know, again,
it took me a while to refocus my
efforts. Anyway, those are all really
bad behaviors, but needing to kind of
think about that a little bit as we're
thinking about improving feedback
cycles, I do think is important. So, I
think without any kind of measurements,
you don't even know if you're at risk
for that. So if all your feedback cycles
are 30 seconds, right? Yeah, you can
make it better, but that's really good.
If your feedback times are are an hour,
that's a huge problem. So I keep saying
the same metric, but I think that's the
big one in terms of implementing
observability in the tool chain from an
organizational perspective. What are the
most common issues organizations
encounter when trying to do that? I
think it's somebody owning the tools
that are around it, right? So if you
have, you know, if you're more than one
team or more than one product
organization. So if you're you're a
single product company, it's pretty easy
to get things moving because everything
revolves around one codebase or one
product. So all of the teams are very
very connected. But if you have kind of
a centralized team that manages, I don't
know, 10, 100, a thousand different
projects, you know, those tools are
usually owned by somebody else and
whatever tool it is, you know, our tool,
somebody else's tool, login collection,
whatever it is. So just the amount of
effort it takes is challenging for
somebody. So a developer comes in and
say hey this build is slow you know we
should fix it and everyone's like yes we
should right but they're like ah I don't
really want to you know request the new
infrastructure or deal with the other
team they don't understand my problem
and so I feel like you know there's
probably some social issues here right
and this isn't just for observability
this is kind of any tool that will
improve your life you know I know people
who have a hard time getting an IDE
license for the same reason which is
mindboggling right you want to talk
about a productivity tool your IDE is
kind of where it starts. So, I feel like
there's some of that that I feel like we
need to get over as a as an industry,
but also the knowledge I don't think is
there. So, like like I said, I mentioned
before. So, you wouldn't put a
application in production without
monitoring. Everybody just kind of
assumes that, right? That's table
stakes. I don't know. It's not shocking
to anybody. If I came to you tomorrow
and said, "Hey, I I've got this tool or
this application we're going to deploy.
My organization probably has, you know,
documents laid out of how it's going to
be monitored. We have playbooks, what
whatever you want to call it. That's
already all resolved, but we don't have
any of that for build systems. So,
there's a little bit of a an
organizational learning curve to get
there. So, how do you see the future of
observability in the tool chain
evolving?
That's a great one. I think the
importance of it is going to increase. I
think from the angle of security
perspective I think it's going to have a
huge impact because you know the rise of
SIG store salsa and toto all these other
things are coming from different use
cases of of getting data out of the
system right so basically for for folks
not in the aware you essentially have
inputs and outputs into a system right
and you want to know what those inputs
are and you want to know what the
outputs are and you want to make sure
there's you know security in place
Right? Like did this git commit actually
come from I don't know GitHub? Was this
thing that was built? Was my binary
built on a machine that was that was
approved and met some sort of criteria?
Great. We have a a structure of defining
that information, signing it, making it
secure and and available. But that's
very similar data, right? If you think
about it, your build tools want to know
the same types of things. What went into
the system, what cames out. Those are
the things you want to track. you could
essentially define policies around all
of that. So if you want to define a
policy for your deployments, so your
your production applications need to say
we're only going to deploy things that
were built on these approved systems.
Well, then you need to have
infrastructure in place and policies and
tooling to know that all of that stuff
actually happened, right? and and you
need to have some alerting that when
those policies are not met then your CI
systems fail or what whatever it is to
give feedback faster to developers. So I
feel like there's going to be pressure
from that angle too that are coming into
the system as well as you know obviously
productivity is a big one. Is there
anything that we miss that you would
like to add? I don't think so. I think
the big thing for me again is we really
need to start thinking about our tool
chains as production systems, right?
they're the production infrastructure
for getting things to production. So
when we start thinking about things that
way, I feel like that removes a lot of
the friction that we have or or how or
at least frames how we think about the
problem to begin with. That's a very
good point. I agree with that. Okay,
that was the last question. Thank you,
Brian, for coming to the show. It's been
a real pleasure. This is Jovann Brun for
Software Engineering Radio. Thank you
for listening. Thanks for having me.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by it
e software magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Common
License 2.5. Thanks for listening.